Hi, welcome to our latest French Revolution episode.
This is the story of the birth of feminism,
the extraordinary, glamorous, dramatic tale of the rights of women.
Marianne is the embodiment of the French Republic.
Marianne represents the permanent values
that found her citizens' attachment to the Republic,
liberté, égalité, fraternité.
The earliest representation of a woman wearing a Frisian cap
– an allegorical figure of liberty and the République –
made their appearance at the time of the French Revolution.
The origins of the name Marianne are uncertain.
Marie-Anne was a very common first name in the 18th century,
and she thus came to represent the people.
The counter-revolutionaries used the name derisively
when referring to the République.
So, Tom, that was the website.
The website of the Élysée Palace,
talking about the great symbol of the French Republic, Marianne.
So this is a symbol that emerges at the point that we've just got to
in the great narrative of the French Revolution,
the summer and autumn of 1792.
We heard last time about the terrible September massacres
that took place as the Prussians were advancing on Paris.
And it's, of course, at this point that people are singing the Marseillaise,
the marching,
the song of the army of the Rhine that has swept through the capital.
But it's also at this point that people alight upon a new symbol of France,
which is this figure of Marianne.
Marianne, who is this woman wearing the Phrygian cap, the liberty cap,
long flowing hair, will become the emblem of France itself.
And I think it's really striking that two of the emblematic embodiments of modern France,
so the Marseillaise, its national anthem,
and the figure of Marianne, the embodiment of France herself,
emerge in precisely these months, the summer going into the autumn of 1792.
And I guess the previous episode that we did where we looked at the September massacres,
I mean, it didn't really portray the revolution in a great light, did it?
I mean, if we're absolutely honest.
Not in the best light, no.
But I think this kind of reminds us that even while people are being dragged out
of prisons and hacked to death, there is also an absolutely invigorating
and inspiring sense of optimism and hope that is inspiring terrible deeds, yes,
but also, you know, it's rallying people to the barricades
and it's giving people dreams of a better future.
Yes.
A future in which all of the people of France will have a stake.
So you mentioned at the end of the last episode,
you left us with this absolute cliffhanger that the Prussians are advancing on Paris,
but you also talked about how there is this new political settlement,
there's this national convention and elections are being held to it.
And you said, you know, if the Prussians break into Paris,
then maybe the convention will never even meet.
A spoiler alert, the Prussians don't end up meeting, advancing on Paris,
for reasons that we'll discuss in the next episode.
And the next episode,
national convention does meet and it meets on the 20th september and the deputies who are going
there they're all going to the tuileries where the royal family had previously been based until
the massacre of their guards and their removal um to what ultimately is their prison so this is now
at the center of the convention which is an expression of in a way popular sovereignty
what is striking about this and it's not just in the french context but in the context of the
whole of global history is that this is a near universal suffrage for men there are no
distinctions of class there are no distinctions of property people may remember back in the mists of
time that we talked about originally there was this idea of active and passive citizens weren't
there that active citizens you had to have certain property qualifications you couldn't have certain
professions all that has gone all males basically over the age of 21 now have the vote and i think
this is a kind of noble and inspiring
you
moment in history no matter what your views on the revolution might be dominant would you disagree
with that or or not i mean maybe don't you think i would yeah i don't find it inspiring at all
well i don't think everybody should have the vote so okay that's the difference between me and the
french revolutionaries so who do you think should not have the vote i probably wouldn't give it to
anybody but i definitely raised the age thing i think probably 30 35 40 and also property i think
you need to be a property you need to own property don't you fine okay the voice of john bull otherwise
you've got no stake in the system um i think you know that you are just teasing i'm sure you are a
democrat tom that has thrown you so much you don't know i can't believe really really know i don't
think i don't really know how to reply to that come on yeah this is this is universal suffrage
this is democracy in action it's the closest to the modern ideal of democracy that we have it's uh
an ideal that uh britain now cleaves to so in that sense you could say that britain is inspired by
this example as well yeah and marianne becomes a model of democracy and she's been inspired and she's
becomes the symbol of it. The reason for that is the motion that is brought before the deputies
the day after they meet on the 20th of September, on the 21st of September, when they essentially
vote to abolish monarchy. Royalty shall be abolished in France is the motion. This is where
the woman who comes to be called Marianne is introduced. Again, to quote from the Élysée
Palace, Marianne is the embodiment of the French Republic. And so how does it come about? How does
this woman appear? How does she come to be called Marianne? It's actually not until the middle of
the 19th century that she's kind of universally called Marianne. But the Élysée Palace thing that
I read at the beginning is wrong. Am I not right in thinking that we know better than the Élysée
Palace? No one. So the Élysée Palace said, you know, who knows where the name comes from? We know
precisely where the name comes from. The name comes from this poem that is written in
October, is it? October 1792. To mark the founding of the Republic.
And interestingly, the poem is not in French. I mean, that's what makes it so fascinating.
Yeah. So it's by a guy called Guillaume Lavabre, who is writing in Languedoc. And he writes this
poem called La guérison de Marianne, The Healing of Marianne in French. And in that poem, Marianne
is clearly an embodiment of the new republic that's been proclaimed. And this is the first
equation of the Republic. And it's a very, very important equation. And it's a very, very
important equation. It's a republic with a woman called Marianne. But unlike the Marseillaise,
it doesn't really spread because it's not as accessible. And it takes a long, long time
for that equation to kind of spread. As I said, it's not really until the 19th century.
And so originally, the figure of France as a woman, she's not called Marianne. She is very
clearly liberty, and specifically, republican liberty. And the emergence of an image of France,
as a woman who embodies liberty, as we said, this is emerging at the same time as the Marseillaise
is being enshrined as the national anthem. And so it's expressive of all the convulsions,
all the excitements, all the kind of incredible process of change that these months in 1792 that
we've been covering in the previous series and in this series are generating. And she appears
very precisely in the wake of the abolition of the monarchy when the royal seal, great golden seal of
Louis XIV, was born. And she appears very precisely in the wake of the abolition of the monarchy when
the royal seal, great golden seal of Louis XVI is melted down and reconfigured. And on the new seal
of the republic, this is where liberty, who will become Marianne, first appears.
So the figure of liberty, we've talked so much about the influence of the Romans in particular
on the French revolutionaries. So this is a very obviously classical figure, basically a goddess
holding the fasces with an axe and a liberty cap. That's right, isn't it? So do you,
is there a little bit of Athena about this figure maybe?
Well, I mean, she's liberty. She's a classical abstraction given female form. And as with so
much about the French revolution, it actually has its roots in the ancien regime. So the painters,
illustrators had been showing liberty as this kind of goddess in the years before the revolution
breaks out. So there was a particularly famous illustration in a book about Henry IV, who was
the great hero of France.
Before the revolution, he was seen as the people's king. And this illustration shows him being
carried up to heaven by liberty, by this goddess. You know, this is kind of allegorical illustrations
and paintings that really have very little cut through, but it's kind of there on the margins.
And actually, I think you could say that the very value of liberty is that she is a kind of a bit of
an empty cipher. She's a kind of an abstraction onto which you can project things. So Lynn Hunt,
the great scholar of the kind of the culture of the French revolution, particular interest in the
role of women in the revolution, she wrote about the figure of liberty, that she represented the
virtue so desired by the new order, the transcendence of localism, superstition and
particularity in the name of a more disciplined and universalistic worship. Liberty was an abstract
quality based on reason. She belonged to no group, to no particular place, which is another way of
saying that the whole point of liberty is that she's quite boring. She doesn't bring any baggage.
And it's important because, of course, the marketing of liberty is also a marketing of the
Republic, and she's being stamped on the seal at the point where people don't really know what the
Republic is about. What's it going to be? It doesn't have any of the kind of the attributes
that a thousand-year-old monarchy has. It doesn't bring the inheritance of symbols that France,
particularly royal France, has been absolutely saturated in. Instead, she almost robs Pierre.
It's kind of chilly, poised, uptight, virtuous. And of course, there are the two obvious contrasts
here. So even though she will come to be called Mary Anne, she's not Christian. She's not the
Virgin. She's a Virgin who is not Christian. And I think that's, as we will see in probably our next
series, what you do with Notre Dame, Our Lady, the Virgin, will be a pointed issue in due course for
the revolution. So liberty, Mary Anne, is not the Virgin Mary. But of course, also, she's not
an earthly queen. And more precisely, she is not Marie Antoinette. She is not an aristocratic
woman. And generally, women who are paintings, images, they're from the aristocracy. The whole
point of liberty is she is not. Right. She's classless, I suppose,
isn't she? I mean, she's not defined by any... And because she's antique, she doesn't represent any
particular group in contemporary France. She's universal.
Exactly. And as you said, there are obviously echoes of Athena, the Greek goddess of wisdom. So
in due course, she comes to be shown wearing a helmet. She's shown trampling down various monsters
representing counter-revolution and monarchy or whatever. So pretty much within a year of her
appearance, her first appearance on the Great Seal of France, she's starting to become a bit more
proactive. And of course, the classic expression of this isn't in this French Revolution, but in a
later one in Delacroix's great painting of liberty leading the people. I'm sure people will have seen
it. Liberty standing there in her liberty cap, urging the revolutionaries on. And I think you
get a kind of presentiment of that in the first revolution as well. But Dominique,
I think there's a kind of interesting question about all this, that France, liberty,
the Republic, the revolution are all being imaged by this figure of a beautiful,
slightly chilly woman. But what does it mean? I mean, does it have any resonance at all
for the actual women who were living through the revolution?
So we started the entire cycle of French Revolution series with a woman,
with Marie-Antoinette and the extraordinary misogyny of the attacks on her. And then,
although virility, masculinity…
friendship martial virtue and all of that these kind of these masculine ideas have mattered
enormously to the ethos of the french revolution there have been moments haven't there when women
have taken center stage so i think you did an episode about the um the women's march on versailles
when the market women go and bring back the king america and the symbolism of it being the market
women i think is really important there isn't it yeah and then of course you've got women who are
prominent in the sans-culottes who are storming the the tuileries who are shouting slogans in the
streets so it's not just a man's revolution by any means absolutely so um we i think we talked
before in the previous series about how the idea of the sans-culotte the the man who is wearing
trousers rather than the britches that is kind of the traditional markers of of wealth and status
how important dress is and there are um there are female sans-culottes
you know they're not wearing trousers but they're wearing kind of coarse woolen skirts
um and they're wearing the wooden clogs that are the markers of of a sans-culotte and they they
wear the carmagnol this kind of um jacket that has ultimately come from kind of revolutionaries
in italy and because of the role that they played in bringing the king and queen from versailles
to paris back in 1789 and as you said because of the role that they also play in um in helping the
patriot heroes who stormed the tuileries in the summer of 1792 they are enshrined as a group as
kind of mothers of the nation but i think there is a crucial difference between the way that women
are portrayed in revolutionary propaganda and the way that that men are because you know we've
talked about revolutionary figures whose names continue to reverberate down so everyone has
heard of robespierre or marat or uh
these are individuals who kind of stand tall in the pages of history but women by and large don't
and that is a trend that goes back to the revolution itself so um we talked about marat
who of course in due course will have a meeting with a woman who's not very keen on him
in his bath but before that he he was very proud of himself as a feminist he marketed himself not
just as a friend of the people but specifically as the friend of women
but when he was a feminist he was very proud of himself as a feminist and he was very proud of
himself as a feminist and he was very proud of himself as a feminist and he writes about women
he never names individuals it's always about the totality of women yeah they are a kind of a mass
of humanity who are inspired by a kind of animating energy and an animating emotional power
they're spontaneous this is key to the to how the the march on versailles is is portrayed they are
not individuals and in that way they are kept safe they're not intruding on the kind of masculine
fear and this carries on even when they're not kind of marching on versailles or uh attacking
palaces or whatever because women in paris in particular which is the cockpit of revolutionary
activity they are very very keen spectators so the sense of particularly women from the markets
uh people you know fish wives as political junkies is very very strong they're generally
not allowed to contribute to the public debate itself but they are given access to the galleries
where spectators gather they take up public seats at the convention when it meets and by and large
male revolutionaries are very appreciative of this so there's there's one when um it turns out that
women are not being allowed in to watch a political session because too many people have gathered
there and one of the jacobin deputies kind of posing like a roman it's exactly the kind of
thing that you could imagine someone in the early pages of livy or plutarch saying he orders that
more benches be brought in so that women are not allowed in to watch a political session
they can sit down these are mothers of families he tells the other delegates they are worthy of
ancient rome and it may be because robespierre in particular is so good at playing the roman
that he is a particular favorite of these these women who come to uh cheer and support the the
various jacobin deputies and the fact that robespierre despite his kind of slight image
of chilly asexuality yeah is an absolute
heartthrob i mean they you know he has all these groupies it's kind of noted by his enemies and
causes them some degree of puzzlement i think but it's not because of that image i would say
the chilliness and the i i think that is the draw isn't it the women think i could be the one who
melts the ice cold incorruptible heart all that but actually we're just talking about women as
spectators here watching men but there are well we've had one woman in particular who's been
a killer so we talked about marion swanette but on the side of the revolutionaries we've had one
woman in particular that we've mentioned a few times in the more recent episodes who actually
is an an agent she has genuine political influence and that is madame roland so tell me about madame
roland so she is the wife of a gerald minister and she essentially is the archetype of the woman
who runs a revolutionary salon so the idea of a salon
where um movers and shakers meet up discuss philosophy or current politics or whatever
again it's something that is inherited from the ancien regime but madame roland sets up the kind
of the the classic revolutionary salon but she's not just a hostess i mean as you said she is an
actor she in a way i mean is much more forceful much much more dynamic much more proactive than
her husband so she is the person who comes up with the idea of recruiting the fed
from across france these are the people who will come singing the the marseillaise from the south
of france for instance so that's her idea and in the um the early months of 1792 as the royal
constitution is starting to implode she is writing letters left right and center so she's writing
letters to briso and his colleagues um accusing them of being time wasters um of uh supporting
the king when his regime is clearly on its uppers
her husband to support the suspension of the king he'd been kind of hesitant about this so she's
very forceful she has very strong opinions and she is able because of her position in the salon
because she has all these amazing connections to let her opinions be known yeah they have an
impact but again there's this she does not herself think that women should play a role in kind of
public politics so she doesn't invite other women
to her salon you know it's hers and hers alone that's very margaret thatcher isn't it's how
margaret thatcher ran her government so madame roland i don't think mr satchel would go this
far but she says women must inspire political endeavor yet without seeming to be contributing
to it right and you mentioned marie antoinette i think it's really striking madame roland is very
hostile to marie antoinette and one of the reasons for this is that she condemns marie antoinette for
being a a malign influence on the
king and therefore on politics generally and so she condemns what she calls the faint rustling of
silk behind the royal curtain the idea that when louis the 16th is being attended by his ministers
marie antoinette is there kind of whispering from behind screens and of course the irony of that
is that these are precisely the terms in which many of her enemies so robespierre danton the
montagnard the people who are opposed to the girondin and madame roland is a girondin
this is how they condemn her as someone who is kind of hiding behind a curtain whispering they
literally say she is the new madame de pompadour she's the new madame du barry she is the overmighty
female favorite who has corrupted and seduced this sort of um the slack-minded gullible men
who flock around her i mean it's a she fits it basically into a standard demonology doesn't she
she does and it's to cast her husband as the new louis the 16th
um kind of venal pliable um emasculated yeah and over the course of that summer as tensions
between the girondin and those who are kind of further to the left you might put it like that
um she becomes a kind of hate figure for for many of the son culotte she's uh i guess
what would she be kind of poly toynbee perhaps right that's the way that which blue collar
trump voters talked about hillary clinton's
and for example nagging uh she's only got where she has because of her husband
um she's always telling us off and telling us what's good for us all of that kind of thing
and i think that it helped it actually you know her her role and the things that are said about her
and the misogyny that is directed at her ironically kind of you know is drawing on
the traditions of misogyny that had earlier condemned marie antoinette it it helps to
polarize the political division between the montagnard and the girondin
and it's kind of striking that it is the montagnard those who are furthest left those who are
most committed to perhaps to the ideals of liberty equality and of course fraternity
brotherhood not sisterhood who are i think the readiest to see female claims to a commanding
role in the revolution as actually being counter revolutionary and of course these you know
on the furthest left the robespierre the marat so on these are the men who most identify
with the model of antique virtue, with Spartans, with the Romans of the early Republic.
And we know what the Romans thought about women being involved in politics.
They thought it was a terrible thing.
Yes, because they saw the role, and Spartans paradigmatically, saw the role of women to be
wives and to be mothers. So in other words, women who are dedicated to the male citizen,
their role is to serve them, to enable them to do their patriotic duty, and then to give them
more sons who can continue to serve the Republic. This is very clearly drawing on Spartan and Roman
ideals. It's an ideal that right from the beginning is there in all the festivals that
are staged, in the rhetoric, all of that kind of thing. It leaves open the question, which I think
we should maybe try and answer after a break.
Are there actually any women who are pushing for full political rights? And if there are,
what is the response to them?
Well, the good news for people who like the rest is history, is that there are such
women, because otherwise there would be no second half. So return after the break, and we will meet
two of them. See you then.
Today's episode is brought to you by A Thousand Blows, the new original series
premiering exclusively on Disney+.
A Thousand Blows is inspired by the original series of the original series, A Thousand Blows.
It's inspired by the remarkable true-life story of the infamous Mary Carr, who led a
notorious all-female London gang, the Forty Elephants. As it's International Women's Day
this week, we thought we'd talk about not necessarily the most notorious women in history,
but some of the most remarkable ones, didn't we, Dominic?
We did indeed. I don't know who yours is, Tom, but the person who we've talked
about in the rest is history that I often think about is a young woman called Sophie
Scholl, who grew up in Germany in the late 1930s, early 1940s. She was a young woman of
enormous earnestness and moral seriousness. She and her brother Hans joined and were
key parts of an organisation called the White Rose Group, which distributed pamphlets and
leaflets across Germany attacking the crimes of the Third Reich. As you'll remember, Tom,
Sophie came to a very sad end, that they were, she and her brother, the White Rose Group. She and
were captured and they were interrogated and tried and executed by the Nazis. And the story of her
in prison, in the Stadelheim prison, in the last hours before her death, and she's sort of praying
and she's completely unapologetic about standing up against the horrors of Nazism. I think it's
one of the most inspirational stories in all history, not just in 20th century history.
Yeah. Such a remarkable young woman. I've chosen a young woman who didn't die for liberty but she
was an extraordinary footballer or soccer player if you're watching this in America. She was called
Lily Parr. She was born in St Helens in Lancashire in 1905. She was part of a huge family, lots of
boys, and she, as a girl, loved playing rugby and particularly football. And when
the first world war uh hit britain um men's football basically got cancelled and so everyone
started watching women's football instead and lily was an incredible incredible player so when she
was 14 she got recruited to play for this um munitions factory called dick kerr's um and she
was only 14 and she scored i think something like 100 goals in her first season uh and she played
right the way through the first world war into the aftermath of the second world war she was
famous for the brutality of her kicking she said to have broken the leg of one man when she took a
free kick she broke another man's arm and footballs then were really really heavy so for her her to
kick it i mean absolutely amazing and what made her sporting ability even more remarkable is that
she loved smoking and she was never seen without a woodbine between her teeth and gradually her
teeth all rotted and fell out uh and in due course
the men who controlled football in um england got resentful of the fame of the the female teams and
so they basically banned them from using the professional football grounds very sad um but
and and so lily uh retired and she became a nurse but she was never forgotten and she's now
celebrated um as one of england's not just greatest sports women but sports people of all time and i
think that she was the first woman to be inducted into english football's hall of fame so you know i
mean she's not up there with sophie scholl but she was a remarkable remarkable woman it's brilliant
isn't it tom that uh women's stories like these are being restored to their proper place uh in
recent history and that's one reason i'm looking forward to this um to this new series so much so
this segment was brought to you by our friends at disney plus so a thousand blows that is a new
original series and it is streaming right now on disney plus globally and if you're watching this
in the u.s it is on
hulu welcome back to the rest is history before the break tom promised you he said he'd got binders
full of women who were pushing for full political rights and actually one of them is an old friend
of the show so a tremendous character who was very prominent in the women's march on versailles
uh cut a very flamboyant figure and that is terjuan de merico so she had kind of pistols
in her belt she looked a bit like a pirate she had a band she had a kind of and a
what adamant like adamant yeah she looked a new romantic exactly she had a kind of liberty cap
she had a fancy hat um she's on a horse cut scrape figure but actually she then gets into a bit of a
mess isn't she terrible scrape yeah a scrape is that what it is it's a scrape so she's captured
by austrian agents tell us about that well because she's actually belgian so she's from liege which
is um under kind of austrian ruled low countries and may 17
90s she goes there very ill advisedly you know to catch up with all her old friends and she gets
arrested by austrian agents put into prison and the austrians see this as a great coup because
she's notorious as a kind of revolutionary amazon and so this is a great prize and they transport
her all the way to austria where she is um kept in prison for for months and months and she's
finally released at the end of 1791 because rather sweetly her jailer has grown very fond of her oh
seems to have been a very kind of very charismatic person and the jailer had obviously uh developed a
bit of a shine for her and so she then gets released and goes back to paris and of course
her role in the woman's march has now been supplemented by the fact that she's been imprisoned
by austrian despots um i mean you couldn't have a kind of better calling card really and so this
gives her a stature among revolutionary men as a hero of the revolution that i think no other woman
there she's done the hard yards she's got the notches in her escutcheon to show that she's
she's really served the revolution so even before her imprisonment she had um she'd spoken at the
cordelier club which is the most radical of all the clubs um and after it she's allowed to to come
and give an account of what she'd been getting up to in prison and everything at the jacobin club
itself so you know these are very very distinctive almost kind of unprecedented markers of her status
a taste of what it would be to be a kind of political player to be not just a spectator at
these clubs but a participant makes it all the more frustrating for her that women are are
essentially kept out of that that they're not allowed to do it yeah and so she pursues a policy
of trying to to counter that so she attempts to found um women's only clubs uh mixed clubs
but it doesn't work um and it largely doesn't work
because women don't really seem to have wanted to participate in them and then in 1792 she gives up
on the whole sit you know sitting around and talking because of course she's very much a
woman for a pistol in a belt yeah and so with paris being threatened she agitates for a woman's
battalion to be set up to help in the defense of paris and again this is turned down when the
attack on the tuileries happens the the attack that that um that results in the massacre of the
swiss guards she's there she's all over it it's very much her scene kind of
brandishing pistols again and for this she receives public honor but i think that she
remains an anomaly because she's taught between the traditional dimensions of the masculine and
the feminine the kind of the active and the domestic the political and the person who stays
at home fostering and looking after the the people who will engage in politics namely men
and in due course as we will see because we'll continue her story in subsequent episodes
this tension it ends up destroying her so just before you move on to the other person you want
to talk about there are other people who who agree with her other women who agree with her and say
especially when war is declared they want to join the war effort so um there are two sisters called
the fernig sisters who took up arms in the defense of valenciennes in the east of france the general
was so impressed by them he promised to put them in the line of fire at the first opportunity
which was read out to the legislative assembly so this is summer 1792 our fathers husbands and
sons may perhaps be the victims of erinema's fury could we be forbidden the sweetness of avenging
them or dying at their sides you cannot refuse us society cannot deny us this right which is
given us by nature unless it's claimed that the declaration of rights does not apply to women
and the legislative assemblies you know what it does it just ignores them because people are
embarrassed and actually in april 1792 there was a declaration of rights which was read out to the
the convention bans women officially bans them from going into battle but that issue of the
declaration of rights brings us to the other great character that you're going to talk about today
who is a great favorite of mine and her name is olymp de gouge so tell us about her i mean i think
you're absolutely right that there are women who listening to the revolutionary rhetoric the talk
about the rights of men draw the logical conclusion that there are women who are not
and say well if men have rights why don't women and as as you said war seems to have been a
particular focus for this the idea that men should defend the country if men can defend it why not
women and there are those who want to do that but equally the revolutionary authorities regard it as
an embarrassment they don't really want to to give any encouragement to it and that's why nothing
really comes of it there is no revolutionary battalion of amazons
defending the patry on the barricades and it's left to one woman in particular to hammer home
for what i think clearly from our perspective seems a monstrous unfairness and as you said
this is this is olymp de gouge a woman who is becoming i think better known pretty much by the
year would you say yeah better known now than she's ever been i would say and that is because
more than anybody else in the revolution
she is exposing this key hypocrisy if there are rights of men then why not rights of women and
she is i think a very attractive figure i mean literally attractive she's um very charming
described in 1770 as one of paris's prettiest women but she's just also her personality is
very appealing she's kind of witty she's i mean she seems fun i think that's probably the best way
to describe it um and
she's born in the long dock but she comes to paris in 1768 when she is 20 years old and she
does so initially as the mistress of a wealthy industrialist from lyon there is all kinds of
gossip in paris that she is a courtesan so there is a paper called la correspondance who writes in
1770 so two years after her appearance in paris that she's born with a pretty face as her only
heritage she is known for her beauty and her beauty is known for her beauty and her beauty is
known in paris for some times solely through the favors with which she gratifies her compatriots
and one of these compatriots it was rumored was dominic your old friend uh the duke of all your
philippe egalite truly terrible man with whom she was supposed to have had yeah an affair whether
she had an affair with him or not she was definitely part of his circle and she goes to
the palais real which people may remember is this kind of great complex of buildings in the center
of paris owned by the duke of all your which in the pre-revolutionary world
was a kind of place of free thinking anything could be published there anything could be said
and this is the the world into which olympe de gouge moves and she becomes a kind of leading
contributor to it she's fascinated by it um she is obsessed by all the ideas and the the currents
of conversation the politics there and what's amazing about this is that her background is
actually unbelievably poor um she
arrived in paris barely able to read or write i mean much debate among scholars as to whether
she could read or write at all and on top of that french wasn't even her first language she
spoke occitan so she would have liked marianne yeah she would yeah exactly her background is
absolutely full of kind of the melodrama that you get in novels of this period so the identity of
her father is very mysterious on the birth certificate says that she's the daughter of a
butcher but there's much controversy about this she liked to hint at the fact that she was a
daughter of a marquis at times she might even hint that she was the daughter of the king so
great kind of excitement and swirl of melodrama there and she had then been forced into marriage
at a very young age to a man she absolutely hated and who again in a very melodramatic way drowned
in a flood and this is what enabled her then to to reject any prospect of future marriage she hated
the institution of marriage condemned it as as a form of slavery and to come to paris i mean clearly
she's a woman but maybe a courtesan as well but she is very very smart and this woman who when she
arrived in paris could barely read or write she very quickly becomes not just a a kind of a
participant in um intellectual debate but she becomes first of all a novelist and then a
playwright so she writes her first novel in 1784 then gets very into the theater so she becomes a
friend of sebastian mercier who we talked about in the previous episode that playwright who
came up with all the horrific details about the death of the princess de lamballe and her most
famous play is called l'esclavage des noirs the slavery of the blacks is a very ripe melodrama
about a young girl being reunited with her long-lost father so olympic is clearly working
issues out there but it is also very very vehemently abolitionist um so she is hugely
opposed to the slave trade
and the impact of this play is such that um the slave trade lobby pay hecklers to go to the theater
and to shout it down and such as the the kind of the the uproar that this generates that the play
can only be staged for three nights and it has to be withdrawn which is obviously you know on one
level very bad for limp de gouge she wants the message to get out there she's going to miss out
on the money that she would otherwise have earned but it does make her famous it makes her a figure
of prestige and status yeah in the intellectual world of pre-revolutionary Paris and by and large
I think it's fair to say that anyone who is a committed abolitionist before the revolution
when the revolution comes is is pretty much bound to be in favor of it yeah of course and a limp de
gouge is she's a big fan of the revolution but with caveats right yeah quite a kind of
idiosyncratic take on it so she always has a very soft spot for Louis the 16th um and again it may
be this thing she identifies with Louis the 16th as a man who's unfortunate in his parents yeah a
bit like she was with her father or maybe she's really his daughter after all well I think I think
she was meant to be the the daughter of um of uh Louis the 15th all right so she's his what does
that make her his with that is it stepsister yeah stepsister yeah yeah half sister half sister oh no
it's too complicated I can't work it out but anyway so she feels that Louis the 16th um has been dealt
a bad hand by his predecessors by Louis the 15th and the people who've gone before and so she wrote
about him an unhappier King than his ancestors is he to be made responsible for their mistakes
so right the way through everything that follows the fall of the Bastille right the way up to the
flight to varenne when Louis the 16th and the royal family tried to escape Paris and France
she's very very you know always sticking up for him when he makes his flight to varenne she's
very very disappointed in him yeah understandably she feels that you know
he's let her down he's let France down but worst of all he's let himself down yeah but she still
feels sorry for him and I think that's reflective of the fact that above all she has she has a big
heart Dominic she feels the sufferings of others deeply yeah so whether it's the you know slaves
in the Caribbean whether it's the poor whether it's the king uh whether it's animals she's a
great animal lover you know she she feels compassion for them all that's lovely we love
somebody with a big heart so I think that this explains
why she comes to feel as she does about the revolution just as the king has let her down
so she feels that the revolution is letting her down so people may remember I can't even
remember which episode it was now we've done so many episodes on the revolution but um back in
1791 France gets its first written Constitution yeah this is the one that Louis the 16th had been
trying not to to sign and eventually he's kind of feels bulldozed into doing it um and it's
passes into law on the 3rd of September 1791 Louis the 16th accepts it 10 days later this is
now the Constitution that is going to govern France yeah and this is the one that offers
a measure of suffrage to men but not to women and Olympia is appalled by this and she says well what
about women why why shouldn't women have the vote why shouldn't women have rights yeah as well and
so 12 days later on the 15th of September she you know
she's written this riposte and she publishes it and it's called very pointedly the declaration of
the rights of woman and of the female citizen so it's an obvious parody of the declaration of the
rights of man and the citizen and it's a marker of her again yeah idiosyncratic take on politics
that she dedicates this to Marie Antoinette it's the last person that you will choose right if you
were worried about your standing in revolutionary Paris
simultaneously a kind of parody of revolutionary idealism but also I think it's ultimate expression
because by echoing the original declaration she's aiming to remind the world what it's missing so
woman is born free and is equal to man in her rights and she's deliberately parodying the the
phrases of the declaration of the rights of man and she is demanding that women share in all these
suffrage and she articulates this in a very famous way and one that looks forward notoriously
to what is to happen in 1793 when she writes woman has the right to climb onto the scaffold
she must equally have the right to climb onto the tribunal so in other words if she can be executed
then she should have the right to govern the laws to vote grimly ironic words very grimly ironic
now what is the response to this declaration of the rights of women there are certainly
revolutionaries who accept male revolutionaries who accept its Force the most prominent of these is the
erstwhile Marquis de Condorcet who we met again ages ago he's a philosopher kind of Enlightenment
Philosoph very very anti-christian he's an economist he's very agitated by polluted rivers
he's a very committed abolitionist um so all reasons why he would he would be sympathetic
to what she's arguing and he he absolutely supports female suffrage and I think it's
not just a limp to gouge who is kind of influencing him on this it's also his own
wife who is a very very impressive woman um called Sophie de Grouchy who is sister of a
guy who will in due course become one of Napoleon's most celebrated Marshals Emmanuel de Grouchy now
quite a lot of relationships in this series and indeed in the rest of history generally where the
man is quite a lot older than the woman so the age gap between Condorcet and Sophie is 20. so
she marries him when he's 22 and he's 42 but it's a very happy match um they're both philosophers so
you can imagine you know they have a lovely time sitting around discussing Diderot or Rousseau or
whatever and she's also a very skilled linguist and Dominic the tremendous news is that her
best second language is English oh good for her if she translated Adam Smith yeah tremendous and
Thomas Payne and Thomas Payne and she actually runs her Sonal unlike Madame Roland she allows
other women to come to her son including a limp to gouge so that's where they would all have met
right yeah and the Condor say they're not kind of card carrying Girondins but they're definitely
aligned with them and I think it's true to say that the Girondins are much more in favor of
uh female participation in public life than um than the montagnards
So even though Madame Roland, she's a Girondin, she's not. It is a kind of part of intellectual discussion among Girondins Salon, and particularly Condorcet Salon, that perhaps there should be female suffrage. And so it's not surprising that Olympe de Gouges, I mean, she thinks the Girondins are great. She calls them torches of liberty.
She also aligns herself with the Girondins. But in general, it has to be said that the reaction to the Declaration of the Rights of Women, when people can be bothered so much as to respond to it, is either hilarity or just utter contempt.
And isn't it interesting that the more hardcore Jacobins, the Montagnards they call, Rob Spierre and his circle, people like that.
They're often among the most contemptuous and the most scornful.
And you would think in other respects, I mean, it's a really good example, I guess, of what some listeners may say is the kind of the patriarchal attitudes, the misogyny, that in other respects, they are so democratic.
But on this issue, they say, women, are you joking? I mean, ha, ha, ha, women voting. Wouldn't that be a great, wouldn't that be a thing?
Yeah. And these are the people who, of course, you know, they're all in favor of Sanko.
Yeah.
I mean, Rousseau has an incredible vein of hostility to any notion of female emancipation, of female suffrage.
He wrote in his novel, which was a massive bestseller, La Nouvelle Héloïse, a brilliant wife is a plague to her husband, her children, her friends, her valet, everyone.
And Rousseau is such a massive influence on the way that particularly young male revolutionaries think that he kind of provides.
And of course, you know, as we've said earlier, these are all people who are saturated in Roman literature.
So they know that the word virtue itself derives from the Latin for man, vir.
Virtus is to have masculine qualities.
And when these young revolutionaries are playing the Roman, we talked about this in an earlier episode, to play the Roman often requires a counterpointing of, you know, the idea that the Roman is a man.
A kind of masculine virtue against a female inadequacy.
So David, the great painter, in 1789, he does a painting of Brutus, the man who expelled the king, the kind of the founder of the Roman Republic.
And in this painting, the man is shown stern, unyielding, flinty in the cause of liberty.
And meanwhile, in the background, you have women having the vapors.
They're kind of in hysterics, kind of screaming and generally losing the plot.
And it is the role of the man to put the patrie first.
Then the family.
It is the role of the woman to stay within the domestic household and to raise citizens who can then go out and play their part, serving the patrie.
I mean, you could translate patrie, right, as homeland or as fatherland, couldn't you?
You absolutely could.
Yeah.
And so for men, radicals, even those on, or maybe especially those on the furthest left, it's this combination, this fusion of the ancient and the cutting edge that serves to justify them.
In their, well, yeah, I mean, their contempt for everything that Olympe de Gouges is arguing for.
But I think the thing that's unsettling perhaps for us today, and certainly for many of the feminist scholars that I read on this, is that it's not just men who are thinking this, a majority of women seem to have thought so too.
And Condorcet, who's in favour of female suffrage, he's really puzzled by it.
And he's one of the people who watch his women idolising.
Roche-Pierre, who is absolutely against female suffrage, and he's kind of really puzzled by it.
And so he writes, one wonders sometimes why there are so many women following Roche-Pierre at his home, at the podium of the Jacobin, at the Cordelier, at the convention.
And he says, which is absolutely right, well, maybe one reason for this is that women are reading Rousseau too.
And La Nouvelle Héloïse, his great novel, I mean, that's a massive with women.
So maybe they're imbibing it.
So Madame Roland is a big fan of Rousseau.
And Rosalie Jullien, who you were quoting in the previous episode, I mean, she was a big fan of Rousseau.
So, I mean, maybe it's that, but I mean, I can't really believe that that's...
It's not just that there is it.
So if you think a hundred years hence, when there are going to be huge arguments about women voting, often among the most vociferous opponents of it are other women.
You know, opposing suffrage campaigns, not just in France, in Britain, in the United States.
However, and don't historians think that effectively a lot of women had internalized the assumptions of the age?
That they have come to believe, they come to believe what they're told, that they have their domestic sphere, which is their domain, and that there is the public sphere, which is the domain of men.
This advert is brought to you by Saley.
So Dominic, I think you should explain to our viewers what Saley actually is.
Tom, I would love to.
Because I'm absolutely passionate about Saley.
Now, listen, Saley is a new eSIM service app, and it's brought to you by the creators of NordVPN.
The brilliant thing about Saley is that you can choose from several affordable eSIM plans in more than 180 countries and eight different regions.
And the amazing thing that I really love about Saley is that with a Saley eSIM, you will always have a connection when you need it.
And best of all,
you will reduce those dreaded roaming fees.
Absolutely brilliant.
And Saley couldn't be easier to use.
All you need to do is download the app, buy a plan, install the eSIM.
And the great thing is that with Saley, an eSIM can be installed only once.
So that eliminates the need for you to install a new eSIM for each country.
It's absolutely brilliant.
It's a brilliant thing, Tom.
It's changed my life, genuinely.
So please download Saley in your app.
Store or by scanning the QR code on screen and use the code restishistory at the checkout to get 15% off your first purchase.
The details are in the episode description box.
I think it's this language of rights, perhaps, that underpins it, which Olympe de Gouges is drawing on.
But it also applies to men.
So one of the striking things about this election to the convention, which is it's the first really full male suffrage.
In any election.
I think our perspective today would be people denied a right to vote would embrace it.
You know, they would feel that a great weight had been lifted off their shoulders, that a great injustice had been righted.
But what's striking about that election is how few people participate in it.
I think it's something like one in six.
Yeah, maybe one in ten.
That must reflect maybe a bewilderment, a puzzlement, simply an inability to understand.
What's being offered on the part of men who are being given this right.
And presumably then the same would be true of women, that this is such a kind of novel way of understanding politics and the role of individuals within a polity that people just can't get a handle on it.
And maybe it's a bit like about slavery, you know, where similar debates are happening.
And it's kind of striking that Olympe de Gouges is an abolitionist as well.
As an enthusiast for female suffrage, that she is, she's arguing for things that today we take so for granted that we can't even understand how people could possibly have thought otherwise.
Yeah.
And yet the fact that she is so scorned and despised and mocked does, I think, remind us of just how revolutionary principles.
That today we completely accept once were, and I think there's a case for saying that, you know, for all her soft spot for Louis the 16th, for all the fact that she dedicates the Declaration of the Rights of Women to Marie Antoinette, there is a case for saying that Olympe de Gouges is as radical, if not more radical than any of the revolutionaries that we've talked about in this series.
Tom, I could not agree with you more.
I think actually, by far, she's the most radical.
So all that the men are arguing for, Robespierre's, the Marat's, whatever.
It's within the boundaries.
It's within the bounds of the imagination.
There have been republics, right?
I mean, England executed its king.
There has been the Dutch Republic.
There's the Roman Republic.
It is perfectly plausible to imagine that.
You might think it's a bad thing, which a lot of people in France obviously did.
But, you know, you can imagine it.
It's not making your head hurt to think about it.
But I think with this, what's clearly the case when she presents that Declaration of the Rights of Women.
You know, when she unveils it, the ridicule, the contempt, the disbelief that greets it is a sign that a lot of people just simply cannot imagine a world in which women exercise political power.
Including women.
Yeah, including women themselves.
Exactly.
I don't want to say prisoners of the same imagination, because that casts people in the past as somehow lesser than us.
We're more enlightened.
And I don't generally like that kind of language.
But I think it's a good thing.
And I think it is fair to say that just as we are trapped by our own preconceptions in ways that we don't even recognize, they are absolutely trapped by theirs.
But I think it also suggests that we are beneficiaries of, you know, the events that we're describing in this series in ways that we may not appreciate, that we may mistake for truths so self-evident that they don't need to be argued for, that that's not what they are at all.
That they are, in fact, kind of.
Radical, intellectual, ideological innovations that ultimately succeed because we come to feel, yeah, they're absolutely right, but when they are first proposed, just seem absolutely kind of mad.
Well, Tom, there are lots of people in the world right now, when we're recording this, who would listen to this episode and would say they are mad.
I mean, there are people right now, you know, in the people who are currently administering Afghanistan.
Or indeed Iran, who would say, you know, a lot of what Olympe de Gouges was arguing was bonkers.
So maybe we shouldn't be entirely complacent about it, I guess.
Yes, well, it's, yes.
But it's nice to hear you finally say something good about the revolution.
So Theo will be pleased about that.
Well, I'm not saying something good about the revolution.
I'm saying about Olympe de Gouges, because as we will discover in a future episode.
Revolution doesn't treat her well, does it?
No, it does not treat her well, which is yet another black mark, I'm afraid.
So, uh, jolly good, Tom, that was absolutely fascinating and, um, kind of overdue.
We should have, um, you know, we've done a lot about men in the revolution.
We've done quite a lot about women as well.
Well, we have, we did start with a woman, I guess.
So next week we will be getting back to the narrative, won't we?
Because I think we left it last time with the Prussians.
Cliffhanger.
They were approaching Paris.
They're 120 miles away and they've just turned to finish off the last French army at Valmy.
And listeners will be excited to hear that there is going to be a thrilling twist to.
The story.
We love a thrilling twist on the rest is history.
Can't wait.
So Tom, what could people do if they wanted to hear that episode now?
Literally now.
They could sign up to the rest is history club.
And not only will they be able to hear both the, um, two episodes yet to come, but they will get a slew, Dominic, a slew of additional benefits.
And just to be very clear, we are a mixed club and Tom, do we treat our male and female members equally?
Yeah, we're all about egalite.
We treat them equally.
Badly and on that bombshell, uh, we will see you next time for the most exciting twist in European history.
Goodbye.
Bye.